[Music]
hey folks welcome back to the Q&A
section of the ninth livestream from the
Dark Horse podcast I am Brett Weinstein
this is dr. Heather huiying to my right
and this is Madison in the background
and this is Madison walking around the
room named for the founding father yes
just ignore the door behind the curtain
all right shall we go to the questions
yeah so we're gonna spend an hour
answering your super check questions
about half the time will be spent
answering questions from the first live
stream in half for the questions that
come in during this one without further
ado first question there are no adults
on gov daily brief last night Burke's
stated the test or 50/50 that's at this
time mark at one 50/50 on Fox News video
available on YouTube the quote is quote
these tests are not a hundred percent
sensitive or specific so if you have one
percent of your population infected and
you have a test that is only 99 percent
and specific that means that when you
find a positive fifty percent of the
time it will be a real positive and
fifty percent of the time it won't be so
I believe that this is picking up on I
mean I guess in most of our live streams
we've talked about they're not really
being any adults but you specifically
said that again today but this you know
I had not seen this we had we still
haven't we haven't gone to find this on
YouTube but this quote does not look
wrong it can easily be misinterpreted
but it's it uses the same kind of math
that I walked us through some with some
fictional numbers last time in the
eighth live stream and basically the
idea is if you have let's just again
make up some numbers if you had a
population of one hundred and one people
and one percent of the population is
infected and there you have a 99%
accuracy rate on the test such that only
1% of your tests provide a false
positive you test that hundred one
people and one of those people who is
actually positive will
come out positive and if the remaining
hundred people one of the people who are
actually negative or one out of 100 will
also come out positive so you will end
up with two positive tests in a
population of 101 people one of which
half in this case is actually positive
and one of which half in this case is
actually negative so that is true and it
changes with the actual background
infection right as the numbers I went
through last time as the background
infection rate climbs the ratio of false
positives to true positives or the ratio
of true positives false positives
changes and as the test in this case you
have a very high specificity of test
which is higher than most tests seem to
have but the higher the specificity of
the test the fewer false positives you
get obviously but what people
misunderstand when they hear oh it's 99%
specific there's only 1% rate of false
positives means that if you get a
positive
you only have a 1% chance of it being
false that's not right it depends on
actually what the background rate of
infection is which to know that we need
more much more data than we have which
is the drum we've been beating the whole
time and you can see this much more
clearly as we discussed at dinner after
our last live stream if you use a
reductio ad absurdum logic if you take
the example of let's say a disease that
does not exist cooties for example let's
say that we came up with a molecular
test for cooties now a serology tests
you mean a serology tests I mean it's
obviously a molecular test they're
calling the antigen test molecular tests
all right so let's say a serology tests
for cooties cooties does not exist and
the tests that we generate has a 1%
false positive rate and we were to a
test every American there are 350
million Americans about so you would
expect 3.5 million people to test
positive in spite of the fact that the
disease we're testing for it doesn't
exist
I get the math right I think so yeah
yeah so anyway that tells you why this
is a problem that even a very small
false positive rate over a large
population will generate a
actually large number of people who are
in that category wrongly so anyway there
it is good
Wow what happened here we I thought we'd
look through all these I don't remember
there just being a link to a YouTube
channel do I didn't see this before a
vampire bat one no so Zach if on your
end if you want to look at the Canadian
15 oh yeah see if there's anything more
than just a link there okay next
question until unless we go back to that
one what homework assignment would you
give the audience to take home with if
you were tasked to challenge America to
begin to become a less tribal and more
pragmatic yeah I mean this is this is
almost easy right this just it's a
matter of generosity of spirit and
simply putting aside your priors with
respect to whether or not other people
are making sense some people don't make
sense but in general you will find
especially you know if you talk to high
quality people if they believe in things
that you are certain or false it may
well be that there's something you need
to learn about it so two things approach
other people with generosity with the
expectation that they may be saying
something that you do not yet understand
about their position and then the other
thing would be the formalization of
Steele Manning that when somebody is
expressing a position that you believe
is incorrect going through the exercise
of figuring out how to say what you
believe their position is so that they
understand and they find your
presentation sympathetic that is a very
powerful exercise in discovering what it
is that's on the other side that you
have yet to see so Steele Manning at
some level at some point you stop saying
that that's what you're doing you just
say let me see if I've got this right
you're saying X and then here's why I
don't believe that right
yeah I guess we actually have a few
friends who are working explicitly in
this realm so please correct me if I get
any of these wrong but I think Peter
Boghossian and James Lindsay's book how
to have impossible conversations
provides some good practical advice here
on effectively how to have conversations
across differences that seem like they
may be too too far to cross our friend
John Wood Jr who was associated with the
organization better angels better angels
I actually work is during lockdown but
what they have been doing is going into
communities and bringing together people
who identify on opposite sides of
usually the political divide but I think
some other divides as well putting them
in rooms together and through your
curated conversations bringing them to
understand to see the humanity in each
other and finally Chloe Chloe Valerie
who but you've had both John and Chloe
yep Dark Horse podcast in fact Chloe's
theory of Enchantment which I am not
intimately familiar with but I trust
from speaking with her at some length
about the work that she's doing really
does a great job of furthering the
ability of people to find their own best
selves and the humanity and others yeah
and actually we know a few more folks
involved in various different things I
would say Michael Zimmerman's clergy
letter project absolutely um it brings
together people of faith and atheists
and has them writing letters to reveal
the depth of their position to each
other let's see why am I forgetting the
name of the letter approach is it the
letter project I don't know yeah in
which people are writing letters to each
other online oh oh great thanks man
sorry so it's the Rathbones
and the I wanna say it's the letter wiki
bry it's not it's not that so it's a
it's just letter wiki that's it is it is
it letter wiki yeah so the impossible
cart that they've they've got a
competition that that closed that I'm
supposed to be judging on you know
people having do
local conversations would learn either
in writing yeah I'm so it's anyone with
the letter wiki anyone who wants to show
up with someone that they have a
disagreement about and have a
back-and-forth
in public with respect I think the
ground rules are basically this is going
to be readable by others and you must
you must be respectful
that's basically it yeah as a general
matter shed your prejudices it's very
inexpensive and you will be overjoyed at
the dividends it pays there's just very
little value in walking around making
assumptions about who's reasonable
you'll find you're you're happier if you
don't do it okay hold on a second then
all right do psychopaths face touch less
ie face touching as a social empathic
emotional telegraphing response versus
grooming oh and the video he included
was vampire back camera trap video cool
so again the question is about
Psychopaths and whether they face touch
less I would imagine there's data on
this I don't know if that's what you're
proceeding from in asking that question
I don't know that this is the case but
there does seem to be something about
face touching and you know we've all had
the experience of somebody does this new
wonder if you have a little something on
your cheek or something like that so
obviously there is some sort of empathic
connection that is expressed sometimes
through touching one's own face so maybe
yeah but I don't know I don't either
correlation implies causation if it maps
on to a pre-existing hypothesis confuses
me so this is something that we talked
about in the last livestream
that Brett said correlation implies
causation if it maps onto a pre-existing
hypothesis this question says this
confuses me does Brett mean supports
rather than mathematically implies
correlation is not mathematical proof of
causality right thank you
right implies doesn't mean it proves it
but and you know there's a lot of
details in terms of how strongly implied
causation is you know a
prediction isn't a very strong
implication of causation a very
surprising prediction that turns out to
be true can very strongly imply
causation but in short what you have is
and this is really you know this is in
the philosophy of theoretical work that
when you generate a hypothesis for how
something works you then generate
predictions from that hypothesis those
predictions are often very narrow but
what is supposed to happen is if those
predictions turn out to be true
especially if they are surprising in
some way that cascades back and it says
the hypothesis I used to generate that
prediction has some evidence to indicate
it is right so that hypothesis contains
a model of how the world functions and a
prediction says this is a way we would
know if that model might be actually
functioning and the prediction turns out
to be true whoa what does the model say
and if I can this risks confusing some
people but let's imagine for a second
that somebody said you know what I have
a crystal ball and it works
and you'd say Yeah right and they'd say
I can prove it here I'll show you I'm
gonna look into my crystal ball and I'm
going to tell you the stock prices of
six stocks for three weeks from today
all right guys obviously full of crap
then the stock prices turn out to land
on those numbers now the question is how
the hell did you do that write something
about the model this person is using
maybe it's insider information we don't
know but to the extent that something is
predicted from some mechanism when the
prediction has turned out to be true it
reflects positively on the mechanisms
ability to see that quadrant and so
anyway implies does not mean nails down
it means implies all right the degree of
the strength of the implication is up
for debate have you seen this quote
corona virus has mutated into at least
30 different strains new study finds so
oh but this is it
excuse me Zak if you want to just show
the show the screen this is the link to
the sea
a chat question but not the link to the
peer-reviewed paper which I have
actually seen and I think we may talk
about this a little bit good let me talk
about a little bit in the next the next
livestream when we talk perhaps a little
bit about names and you know what it
means this is it current a virus at all
but obviously at one level I think we
can we can take that down now Zach I
thank you it is we suggested early in
these live streams that this was
beginning this was going to be mutating
that there was already evidence that it
was mutating what it means for something
to be a different strain is of course a
hard to nail down definition and and
there will be disagreement about how big
a change mean it takes before immunity
for instance is no longer valid for the
newly mutated strains but it shouldn't
surprise anyone that given how fast this
thing is moved and how quickly it has
spread across all manner of environments
that it is mutating fast there is
evidence for instance that I think I
think most of the cases on the eastern
seaboard in the United States are coming
out of Europe rather than coming
directly function we can already tell
bat with phylogenetic analysis from the
genomes of the various viruses in these
various places that tells us that this
is changing very fast yeah I would say I
haven't seen this paper I haven't looked
at it but in some sense it's a very
funny headline it's undoubtedly mutated
into innumerable strains that some of
these strains then take hold such that
we see a large population that are
downstream from some mutation that we
can recognize oh this is the strain from
over there that's really what's being
discussed undoubtedly so how many
strains wow I can't imagine even how you
would go about calculating it because
it's going to be some substantial
fraction of the number of infections or
maybe even the number of viral particles
out there but most of those
mutations will be an almost immediate
dead end some of them for cause because
they actually make the virus worse
some of them for random reasons just
because most of these infections or at
least most of these particles will fail
to transmit to anyone else so the very
fact that something takes hold tells us
something interesting and in fact
there's some hope in it too it's
potentially frightening but in general
as we've discussed before these
infections tend to evolve towards a
benign nature some of the evolution is
on the part of the critter being
infected and some of it is on the part
of the pathogen but nonetheless the fact
that mutations are spreading isn't
inherently good or bad doesn't it the
question is are those infections more
pathogenic are they more contagious are
they more benign that would tell you
whether it was a positive or negative
thing yeah there's been some suggestion
also for instance that I think it was L
and s named strains that the L strain
was incredibly variant and much more
often deadly than the S train much much
less so and that we should expect we
should expect to see more of that as we
get more and more reliable data can you
both possibly in future talks or now
discuss how game theory and critical
thinking skills could be integrated into
k-12 education from a frustrated middle
school teacher trying to change a bad
system oh man I feel you yeah I would
say games games lots of games games that
make the kids think that the teacher has
gone crazy and has just declared every
day a snow day I mean this is really
what school should look like it should
be full of games and exercises that are
so much fun that kids don't even realize
that you're educating them yeah we need
to generate those things yeah but I mean
humor you know what he used to say to
students after you'd made them laugh for
a long time if you're laughing you're
not learning clearly the opposite being
the case
Yeah right you tend to be able to learn
better when you are relaxed and easy and
having a good time being outside your
outdoor games physical games games that
integrate both your mind with your body
yeah we we we would often actually you
know play ultimate with students and
occasionally take a take a timeout to
talk about physics right yeah actually
you know it's amazing in the end what's
made of physics no question I just
wanted to thank you both and Zach for
the opportunity to hear you both discuss
the matters of the day and your
evolutionary biology perspectives thank
you Christopher
are there any studies measuring telomere
length of human populations depending on
ethnicity breeding habits or cultural
factors any studies on telomere length
of offspring conceived early versus late
in life by the same male question such a
good question I'm not prepared to
discuss the state of the work on
different populations yes these things
have been studied not as systematically
as I would like maybe some stuff has
happened since I was deeply tuned into
that literature I will say on the point
about males early and late in life there
is this one tantalizing result that I
remember from back when I originally did
this work that said that the telomere
lengths in sperm produced by males late
in life had longer the it was longer
telomere length it's later in life that
a sperm was produced and this really
yeah this makes perfect sense in a way
because as we discussed last time
environments in which you have a good
chance of living longer our ones in
which your ability to to basically
maintain your tissues longer matter more
if you're gonna die young as a result of
violence then the fact that your body is
capable of remaining viable until you're
80 doesn't matter very much if your
environment is purged of violence so
you're gonna live longer than having a
body that has those capacities is more
desirable so how do you how does
selection detect how safe the
environment is well one
in which males are producing offspring
later in life is one in which those
males have reached later in life and
therefore this would be a very good
mechanism for adjustment of telomere
length on a very short time scale
fascinating this is a bribe to get you
to vote for Biden Wow well here's the
thing I have heard that everybody has
their price I don't know if that's true
but I know you're nowhere near mine may
I suggest a different path or mine could
you possibly direct the finances that
you're gonna push our way to get us to
vote for Biden in the direction of Biden
to get him not to run that's what I'd
like to see if I'm following the logical
conclusion of the damage hypothesis does
this mean that working out daily for
example weightlifting would also
accumulate damage and shorten say their
lifespan
that's it another great question yeah it
really is actually yeah and I think
there is boy I don't have access to it
here and it's only kind of vaguely in my
head but I feel like there's some
evidence now that pushing yourself
beyond certain you know close to your
limits with regard to what you can
possibly you know you're I'm trying to
think if it's like strength or
cardiovascular capacity or what exactly
the things are that have been measured
at doing that in a regular basis can
cause at least short-term decreases and
immune response and yes you are
definitely you know what is what is
recovering from a hard work out doing
it's dealing with all those micro tears
and your muscles now muscles are one of
the fastest repairing tissues out there
so I don't know about telomere lengths
in muscles compared to other tissues in
the body as I mentioned before muscle
skeletal muscle is multinucleate and so
it's a different kind of tissue with a
different spectrum of hazards and and
and the like so the analysis is really
hard to compare to something like
cardiac it's all it's at least not a
simple prediction but I would say it's
not that working out is necessarily
going to advance your level of damage in
fact there is some you know there's some
it up to a point but what we're getting
at here is the question is are you doing
more damage to those tissues than is
justified by the advantages you know
strengthening your heart for example
takes the wear and tear off the heart
muscle as it pumps blood through a
healthy body so there's a benefit and
there's a cost and really you can pretty
well predict that the problem is going
to emerge and become critical as you
push the exercise regime to a limit that
up to a point the exercise is going to
be positive it's not to say that there's
no wear and tear and certainly the type
of exercise you choose has a lot to say
about it so for example running on
concrete is particularly bad because
concrete is particularly unforgiving
running on asphalt is better because as
much as concrete and asphalt seem
similar they're not the asphalt is a lot
more give to it and running on a trails
is better yet for not just because
trails are more forgiving but because
you're also getting more information
into your feet and up into your body
about the kind of terrain you're on and
what kinds of muscles need to be used
yeah running on a trail would be better
until you twist your ankle at which
point it can be worse but but anyway the
question is are you doing damage and how
much and doing some damage in order to
make yourself physiologically healthier
is obviously going to be a win but doing
lots of damage is certain to be a loss
okay is that how much time are we at
okay so we're gonna try to get through
these next few questions before skipping
to you the next live stream okay okay
in a youtube interview I heard Brett say
that gender differences can be observed
in trees that is males are Randy and
females are coy can you explain more
well this is primarily a piece of advice
for people who were trees oh no for one
thing they don't freeze
they never listen but for people who hug
them you know if you have a strong
sexuality in which you only favor males
then you want to know which treat no
this is not the pathway the point is
it's not trees in particular its
flowering plants and the point that we
made on Rogen was that if you look
inside of a plant that has both male and
female parts in the same flower and
there are lots of plants that do yeah
hermaphrodite they exhibit the same
reaction to effectively casual sex that
we see in humans which is to say the boy
parts of the plant are randhir and more
excited about mating with any old plant
that'll have them and the girl parts put
the boy parts through a test that
involves a long corolla tube where the
pollen grains have to reach the ovaries
so it's basically like a physical
manifestation of coyness and my point is
this ain't no accident this is a law of
nature that has to do with the level of
investment that follows fertilization
the pollen grain has nothing to lose it
might as well try to fertilize whatever
it lands on because that's the one shot
it's going to get whereas the ovule in
the plant has a large investment and
being picky and choosing those pollen
grains that are from exactly the right
species and maybe even some subset of
those that have particularly good
characteristics is beneficial
so no accident males across the biota
tend to be more enthusiastic about
casual sex and females tend to be more
coy and it has nothing to do with humans
okay five more questions before we skip
skip to the next one but we're going to
be quick about these okay does eating a
diet more native to your ancestry
provide any benefit to one's health this
is a very interesting question we could
again go on for quite a long time on it
our dog hasn't even you know that was
our dog groaning in the background who
does not eat a diet native to her
ancestry as it tends to be kibble and
the occasional banana yeah quite
possibly and this is a book that I don't
100% recommend but I do find
interesting food genes and culture
eating right for your origins by Gary
Paul NAB Han so I saw this question that
I actually own this book and no we said
clear it is so I thought I'd bring it
here
one thing that is certainly true is that
there will be no universally best diet
for all humans because we have different
histories because some of our ancestors
most of our ancestors most recently have
been farmers and therefore the idea that
we are only adapted to the life of an
afront of an African hunter-gatherer is
absurd
there are very few of us who have no
agriculture in our background until say
the Industrial Revolution but even so
compare you know you wouldn't expect
Maasai and an Inuit to be best served by
the same diet given what their people
have been eating over the last at least
hundreds of years so interesting
question yes probably to some degree
anyway eating a diet more native to your
ancestry will provide health benefits
next question
if languages get simpler over time and
since we're doing fine with simpler
languages why does natural selection not
select for simplicity for early humans
which would have been easier and faster
there's a problem with the premise of
this question languages don't get
simpler over time and in general we see
complexity evolve across all systems you
add something I'm gonna I'm gonna try to
rescue the meaning of this question okay
good all else being equal it is almost
undoubtedly true that language has
become simpler over time that does not
mean they become net simpler over time
in other words if you take the English
language the number of things that
anglish has to describe relative to four
hundred years ago is large and so that
complexity has been borrowed from other
languages it's come from a lot of
different places but from the point of
view of saying X thing to the extent
that there is a way to make it more
efficient to get there it is likely to
be weakly favored so I'm gonna I'm gonna
push back we don't we can't do this now
really but um I would say that not not
only do we end up with more redundancy
over time like you have rather than one
word for a concept you end up with you
know ate mostly overlapping words for a
particular concept so that's that's some
kind of complexity but more interesting
yet is the amount of metaphorical
building so you have you have things
like talk you know Tim higher
temperatures are up
why are higher temperatures up so that's
sort of an obvious place where metaphor
exists in language but when you really
start looking at the kinds of ways that
we talk in in English which is obviously
the language that we know best
we have metaphor upon metaphor upon
metaphor and actually some linguist have
been able to track some of those so here
I'll recommend another book that I find
a totally extraordinary called the
unfolding of language by a guy named
guide deutscher it's a book I've and he
takes an evolutionary approach to both
the origins of and the spread of
languages and it's his point around the
ubiquity and increasing embeddedness of
metaphor that makes me say with you know
I feel pretty confident that languages
do not get simpler over time well I'm
not sure I'm not sure we're actually
disagreeing is what I said was that all
else being equal they will get simpler
over time but that they're accumulating
the ability to say more things and
therefore you will not get a net
decrease necessarily especially in
modern times okay all right okay
if you compared the DNA of a newborn
baby to the DNA of the same person 90
years old with the DNA sequence be 100%
identical or can it change over the
course of a lifetime Thanks love the
stream in order to answer the question
that I think you're trying to ask you
have to sort between what we call the
soma that is all the cells that are a
dead end because they cannot produce a
new person and the germline that is the
tiny number of tissues that actually go
on to generate new people the gametes
the Spearman YAG now a hundred percent
identity between the newborn and the
older person in the germline not a
hundred percent but the germline is many
cells and a male it's spermatogenic
tissue and so you can get a mutation
that will change future generations in a
cell within the germline
things are a little different for
females amongst mammals because females
produce their eggs before birth they
produce them but not entirely not
entirely but almost entirely the
majority of them are produced prior to
birth and it is always fascinated me why
that would be the case but anyway it has
implications for mutations that would
accrue later in the soma you can get all
kinds of things happening mutations are
what causes tumors most mutations won't
cause a tumor but yes there are lots of
bits of cellular damage that occur in
tissues in the soma but they have no
implication going forward because most
of them have little consequence and they
have no mechanism for getting into a new
person anyway regarding open peer-review
what kind of systems are needed for
example Yahoo Answers versus Stack
Exchange stock-exchange systems lead to
better info how to reward good research
while minimizing negatives of good
hearts law quickly I'm not sure a good
hearts lies I'm trying to remember which
of them it is but in any case I'm a fan
of Stack Exchange I'm a fan of Cora I
think there's a lot of room for us to
tune into each other's expertise and to
use Mehcad I'm also a fan of Reddit all
of these things are flawed in their own
way but the basic premise that we can
afford to have anybody weigh in on
anything and then we can promote answers
that have greater currency I think
that's all to the good
and I love seeing a proliferation of
these mechanisms it didn't exist in the
world you and I were born into and I
think it's clearly an improvement yep
very much so good hearts law is
summarized at Wikipedia or by Marilyn
Strathearn is when a measure becomes a
target it ceases to be a good measure
mmm that's good
okay that's very good okay last question
that was skipped we'll switch to the
questions from the current live stream
is no in seeing and pursuing a bigger
game is this where your Explorer modes
enter could the bigger game be
accomplished with the singularity
but at the cost of humanity itself if so
do we pull the trigger it's a big
question to end on yeah you know there's
a lot of I don't I won't call it jargon
because that's dismissive but there's a
lot of terms in there that we would have
to be careful to make sure we knew
exactly what we were talking about were
we to step into the bigger game we would
very clearly be across an event horizon
in other words one of the features of
the bigger game would be that we can't
exactly tell where it would lead us and
so in fact a principle that I think
governs whether or not we can take a
particular proposal about a future world
seriously is does that proposal pretend
to understand the implications of what
is being proposed and if it's too
specific we know it's not right because
the evolutionary force will take
whatever we deliver it and will modify
it and so what I want to see is
proposals that outline what the
objective of the change is and propose a
way to navigate towards that objective
but are sensitive to the fact that if we
try to blueprint the future we're gonna
screw it up if we try to navigate to the
future it's readily possible so let's
take on a navigation metaphor rather
than a blueprint metaphor because for
one thing it's much more likely to work
all right
SEC what's the time all right so we're
gonna take 25 minutes to answer the
questions that have come in during this
live stream in the order that they have
come in unless something feels like we
don't feel like answering it cooties as
a concept that is literally false
metaphorically true question mark might
have arisen out of a legitimate need to
social distance during some past
academic yes I have wondered about this
and in fact I get a little looking into
it at one point I'm trying to member
what the outgrowth was I think it might
have been lice there was something you
know there's obviously very little truth
to the fact that
girls carry lice that boys can catch and
boys can I stick girls can catch I mean
one could rescue a premise out of that
but it does suggest a misunderstanding
but anyway yeah of course cooties could
be a trainer for some sort of distancing
absolutely this person is asking if Twi
V podcast channel is a great place to
get solid info on viruses or he says
that and then he asks thoughts I don't
know it do you know I feel like I fit
but I don't I have encountered it yet so
no it's oh well you know that that's
what are the top frequently questioned
answers on the subject of kovat 19y -
the top frequently questioned answers in
the subject of cove at 19 well that's
that's interesting I don't know what it
means well so what what what is accepted
as the truth that turns out to have a
lot of people saying I'm not sure that's
right so I would say it from it for
instance early on the CFR the case
fatality rate and now people are talking
about the infection fatality rate was
from a lot of us getting pushed back
because of the so called denominator
problem because we simply had no idea
still have no idea because the tests
aren't being done what the actual
background infection rate is so how
things are moving around here
so what else that we were taught you
know we were told was true by the
government's by the CDC the who you know
yeah there's masked nonsense which seems
to have been a cover story for
redirecting medical supplies it may may
have needed to be redirected towards
medical professionals but there's that I
would say in general the fact that we
have such bad data on what actually
happens in infections is a reflection of
the fact that we have not been
systematic about
identifying a population and testing all
of the things that we would like to
answer within it so I said in the last
livestream that I thought military bases
might provide a place of study these are
not a population I want to see
experimented on I would be dead set
against that but I would like to see us
take a population that has a describable
limit and figure out what we can learn
about the progression of this disease in
that population for example I would like
for somebody to be able to say what is
the effect on the lungs of people who
have had a non symptomatic or low
symptomatic infection and then somebody
else be able to bring up a database and
say you know on this military base these
people have had a low symptomatic
infection and are four weeks out from
their last indication or something like
that let us give them x-rays and see
whether they show evidence of lung
damage then we could know whether or not
that damage accompanies these low level
infections or if these low level
infections are low damage and may
provide immunity that would also be a
very interesting finding
I think we're some of the only people
I've heard talking about that though so
in terms of frequently questions answers
at this point the dog is shaking the
entire studio at this point almost
everything has been questioned but the
questions are often just kind of
scattershot because people have begun to
distrust all sources of information what
are potential evolutionary components to
lucid dreaming as one who is only lucid
dreams as far as I can recall it often
feels more like an affliction than a
benefit um you know act about this a
little bit last livestream is where
that's coming from yeah I would just say
we have cautiously taken a a stance in
favor of hacking ones environment and
hacking oneself
lucid dreaming may not be for you
hallucinogenic drugs may not be for you
but to the extent that you are looking
to explore certain things they could
potentially provide exactly the
tool you're looking for and my point
would be lucid dreams happen
occasionally too many people who are not
trying to have them and then other
people cultivate the ability to get into
that lucid state it did occur to me
after our last livestream that the most
important piece of advice that I found
in the Stanford sleep research on lucid
dreams was that the way to trigger that
state more regularly involves
introducing into your normal waking life
the question am I dreaming such that
every time something slightly odd
happens you ask yourself that question
it becomes habitual and then you find
yourself doing it while dreaming and it
dawns on you yes actually in fact this
is a dream at which point the question
is can you remain asleep where does that
instantly wake you up so anyway it's a
technique and I would advise those who
are interested to try it and then once
you get there ask yourself am I better
off doing this and I certainly found
that I was better off for it but that
you know I'm not still doing it because
it had a cost it was exhausting and I
got out of it you know maybe I'll go
back to it someday but I got out of it
what I got out of it and I've moved on
but it was worth I question seems to be
coming from someone who has no control
and it's her default
I think her default state is in the
opposite direction for most people's
default state so being stuck in lucid
dreaming territory would indeed
I feel like an affliction I think yeah I
I would say final thing on this is the
most interesting thing about the state
was the fact that it was not a state of
total control not even remotely
it was a state in which I had control
over what I did in dreams but I had
almost no control over what the world
around me did and I found that division
to be very evolutionarily significant in
other words it said it's like life it's
a little bit like life is about right
and so anyway it's certainly worth
seeing whether that dividing line is in
the same place for you as it was for me
and if so what those implications
be for the utility of dreams good so the
next question I think is one that we
just answered from the last live stream
about languages and getting
morphologically similar simpler over
time so we're not going to replay that
conversation what can evolutionary
biology teach us about fixing our
political systems specifically the two
party monopolies least of two turds
keeps us in hurts that's good I would
say first of all it may not be
evolutionary biology per se but game
theory I believe certainly tells us that
first-past-the-post voting is liable to
default into two incoherent parties and
our parties are beyond incoherent
they're also deeply corrupt but there is
a lesson in building a system in which
corruption is avoided based on
structural protections against its
evolution it's not a simple problem but
it is a tractable problem and anyway I
think any effort at a better society
will its success or failure depends
critically on whether it has nailed the
question of capture and how to prevent
it if you were in charge of the kovat 19
response for the US what would you do
right now I think I spelled it out a
little bit in my description of what if
Trump did it we should all get behind
which is to say make happen and
distribute and get tested for both types
of tests antigen and antibody testing as
widely as possible as quickly as
possible and as that is happening as
quickly as possible
explain to the public what various
results will mean in terms of release of
lock down in stages and how soon it
might be able to happen you know what
kinds of base infection rates suggest
that we might be moving towards herd
immunity if we've got
you know a significant number of people
who've already been infected
can we start doing track and trace on
people who develop new new cases this
you know information that's based on a
plan from our government that is based
on actual information is what we need
and I have seen basically nothing no
evidence that the people at the highest
levels of government are doing much to
get testing widespread quickly and for
my part I would identify populations
that could be studied with respect to a
couple different questions a what is the
what are the basic facts about the
infection and the damage that comes with
it
and what is the consequence of various
different lockdown readings so among the
many things you could study in a
military base context would be you could
test the effect of various relaxation of
the lockdown protocol in particular what
happens if you free people to go into
the outdoor spaces maybe you even
encourage them to go to the outdoor
spaces maybe you have provisions for how
you would be expected to do it but if it
is true that these things need to be
locked down then certainly we should
find that out before we unlock them down
and if it is true that people in
lockdown can be freed to do those
activities and it won't cause a jump in
the infection rate and it will cause a
jump in psychological health based on
not being you know cooped up in your
house then we should know that so I
would just say look there's no mystery
here this is a set of phenomena it's
study abou in the same way every other
set of phenomena is study about the way
you would do this properly is you would
identify a population that was
representative enough and then you would
stay to start taking really good
thorough data so you could ask any
relevant question quickly and get an
answer and then we could stop doing what
we're doing now which is basically
responsible
blindly based on our intuition it could
just be done much better with data I
will say I'm not sure this is directly
apropos but as we've we've begun talking
at dinner about my and our growing
concerns about sort of the ongoing
maintenance to people's bodies and
psyches that aren't happening during
lockdown that you know medical offices
are closed dental offices are closed I
don't know about therapists actually
presumably some of that can happen
remotely yeah but you know we've talked
a lot about about movement and being
outside and such but there are lots of
other things that people need you know
if this were an excuse me if this were
happening two years ago and I was still
I personally was still in the physical
state I was in
post boat accident I suffered a
remarkable boat accident in Galapagos on
our study abroad trip and I was unable
to be seeing the you know the do and a
couple of bodywork people who really
helped me get back together I would be
falling into disrepair
rather you know at this point it having
been whatever five or six weeks since
I'd been able to see anyone and you know
we are lucky that none of us is in such
a state at this point we're all able to
be healthy and to maintain health
through the activities that we can
engage in in our home and near our home
but there have to be many people and it
has to be a higher risk the older they
are who actually need sort of
maintenance work at some level and
talking about the lockdown as if it's
binary has the same problem is talking
about you know the effect of the
diseases of its binary it's not you die
or you're fine and it's not you don't
leave your house or everything is open
you know it's probably going to be a
while before nightclubs are deemed safe
but going to your doctor or your massage
therapist or what you know any any
number of types of things in which
people can be safe but do and do end up
in close contact should be possible
much sooner yeah it occurs to me that's
probably isn't the right concept but we
need something like Maslow's timeline of
need there are things which you don't
need on the scale of a few weeks you
might mean on the scale of a few months
this is reference to Maslow 20th century
psychologist ish I think hierarchy of
needs is definitely a pyramid yeah yeah
and anyway the point is to say that
something is or isn't essential you know
is buying pants essential I was on
whether or not you've got pants right
exactly at the point that all your pants
are no longer functional it becomes kind
of important well in this this is too
too silly but we've got a cat that eats
socks and you and Zachary have both lost
a fair number of socks to this cat and I
went to get socks for Zachary to the
site that I usually get socks from when
they're closed
there's no they're just they're closed
for business for the for the foreseeable
future yes except that all the dog
people in our audience are thinking the
solution to this problem is obvious
we'll say we have our dog in the room we
don't have any of the cats in the room
here our dog does not make sucks though
so this this is a problem yeah she's
looking for good work and that hasn't
heard to her yet anyway there is sort of
a shortage of socks in our environment
and and fewer abilities fewer routes to
getting them there I'm actually missing
more left than rights which is weird
do you do you believe that infinity goes
macro and micro I'd never thought about
this before I don't think so I think
there's a there's a hard floor zero zero
and nothingness are real and and
infinity can go out and up and yeah I
I've always thought the zero was the
loneliest number I realized I'm in the
minority on that one but anyway yeah
zero does seem to be a hard floor yeah
you could go fractional infinitely
presumably but I think yeah I'm gonna
I'm gonna avoid this question as a non
mathematician I feel I'm going to get
myself in trouble yeah well your
brother's a mathematician
mine isn't so that's right now in
biological versus civilization
timeframes do viral outbreaks discourage
rule-breaking or rebellious behavior is
that good long-term human culture I
can't quite follow there's there's a lot
of it's a lot going on in this question
if we just take the middle part do viral
outbreaks discourage rule-breaking or
rebellious behavior it's not clear to me
why they would it's also not clear to me
that our relationship with viruses is
not largely I want to be very careful
about this it's not like we wouldn't
have had any viruses but the number of
viruses that a person encounters in a
lifetime I think has radically changed
as a result of the fact that all of
these things that would circulate in a
small population are now going global
and so you know there are dozens of
viruses circulating every winter and
things like this so anyway it's not
clear to me what the historical
circumstance would have been and what
its interaction would have been
therefore with personality
characteristics like the ones you're
talking about interesting question
though mm-hmm how do we approach the
insidiousness and addictiveness of the
sugar in our food supply food a holic
synonymous what's a good first step for
better health for the individual and for
society it's a great question
sugar does seem to be one of the hidden
pieces of the puzzle that until pretty
recently some combination of legitimate
confusion and you know big sugar for the
sugar Lobby is managed to keep obscure
from many people you know I know salt
and fat we are not medical doctors salt
and fat do not seem to be certainly not
fat and even cell does not seem to be
the enemy of human health that that we
were told it was we're not doctors but
we are hungry and and obviously and
there's a lot of different kinds of fat
so there are plenty of fats that are
plenty bad for you
but plant fats and animal fats yes even
animal fats are far better from you then
again fats that were synthesized in a
lab on average so sugar is has been in
short supply in our diet in the past as
salt has eyes fat has which explains our
cravings but the ability to turn beets
and sugar cane into crystalline form and
bake them into deliciousness is quite
new in you know why it's a few hundred
years old really right so well it's a
good first step and I think at some
level the last five or ten years we've
been beginning to take this step that
increasingly people are aware of of how
toxic sugar actually is but I don't off
the top of my head have a better answer
than that yeah I would say I don't think
all sugars are equal they're definitely
too easily accessed and we are very
tuned into their presence because of
their obvious high caloric value yeah
fructose the sugar and maple syrup far
better for you than sucrose derived from
beets and cane sugar but the basic
advice would be you're not gonna regret
weaning yourself off of especially those
suspect sugars and substituting other
stuff yeah and you know we say that as
people who eat sugar it's not that we
are when you're pure in this regard okay
next question five minutes more okay
we'll get through as many of these as we
can do you know if there are any studies
regarding the mental health cost of the
shutdown
I'm sure the effect is negative but it's
hard to quantify we should think about
it when talking about how long the
shutdown will last yeah I mean I think
we've we have been talking about it I am
not aware of any studies if anyone is
maybe you know either
son send a link to one of our emails
which you can find on our webpages but I
don't think any such work has been done
yet I read something
I'm not prepared to put any weight on it
but I would say I wouldn't leap to the
conclusion that certainly it's going to
be negative for some people and over the
longer it lasts probably the more
negative for the more for more people
but there some people are finding a
great deal of purpose in being freed
from what they were doing and being put
into service generating something new
and productive to do if this is you
don't distrust it it's important one of
the things that modern civilization has
done is it has robbed us of meaning and
yes this is a terrible predicament but
if it has given you something to think
about and some way to re-engineer your
life and innovate go with it you know
it's this is this has been costly if
there's some upside to it that's all to
the good
hi my name is dawn Weisberg and I'm
wondering what you think about eric's
your brother's idea on legend that's the
gated institutional narrative and how do
we break that gate Cheers
yeah I'm a fan of this idea I've
certainly encountered the gated
institutional narrative more times than
I can count and you know is that the
precise description of it you know
obviously it's a it's a metaphor but it
stands for something real how the Djinn
happens how it functions is up for
discussion but let's put it this way
those who have encountered it have a
pretty good idea what Eric is talking
about and if you haven't encountered it
then you ought to listen to those of us
who have and say wow isn't it
interesting that people who you know
don't seem crazy are talking about
encounters with this you know glass like
barrier that prevents things that need
to happen from happening prevents things
that need to be said from being voiced
in certain places it's real I don't know
how it came to be but it's definitely an
obstacle to progress two more questions
and then we'll sign off is this the end
of the Industrial Revolution has nobody
noticed that the
system has failed it is starting to look
like billions of people that rely on the
system will die many of us have noticed
that the system has failed that said it
can get far worse and I know many of the
people who understand that the system
has failed I have a belief that
basically okay collapse is coming let it
happen and then we'll rebuild no you
won't we have to retool without collapse
occurring and that is a difficult and
frightening prospect it's the first time
this has happened to humanity that were
actually utterly dependent on the
fragility of the system not having it
grind to a halt because we are all
dependent on it even those of us who
understand its brokenness okay next one
is not a question but just that you have
been sent onto your website address
paper on exercise and aging so final
question what do you guys think about
states like Georgia reopening
non-essential businesses on the 27th I
assume that means the 27th of April here
in Oregon there's been talk about end of
May as a as a reopening date I hadn't
heard that it really depends on what's
going on in those states to some degree
it seems early on the other hand some
states are far less affected on the
other hand how is it that you're then
going to patrol the borders I would say
in addition I am very concerned about
what it is that will trigger the various
races to the bottom between the states
between nations between people and let's
say let's give Georgia the benefit of
the doubt here let's say Georgia knows
something about its own epidemiology
that actually justifies it going off
lockdown but then other states start
looking at Georgians behaving normally
and begin to feel that Georgians are
pulling away and that they need to get
back into the race
the race to the bottom gets triggered
all too easily and lots of places can't
afford to go off lockdown so as I've
been saying now for weeks we need to
think about the game theory and we need
to figure out at the moment the world is
on pause
the point you start taking parts of the
world off pause a whole different thing
unfolds and the importance of what will
unfold is would be difficult to
overstate it's really potentially a
major disaster epidemiologically and in
other ways as well so let's be really
careful not to rush to reopen things and
as I said earlier let's study ways that
we could relax the lockdown without
triggering such a cascade so not a
question but one last thing someone
writes in that he listens to a lot of
streaming and that we should be asking
you the listeners to all hit the like
button the likes should reflect the
people in chat so here we are asking you
guys yeah could you hit the like button
the subscribe button maybe the notify
button we would appreciate all those
things it is a an excellent way to
support us and it costs you nothing so
that's right please do that yeah so
we'll be back on Saturday at 12:30 at
noon thirty noon thirty Pacific time
which will allow some of our fans in
Europe to tune in live potentially and
possibly we will even deliver some of
the podcast in European Wow I know it's
the continental European or can we go to
the UK I'm not ready to get specific but
you'll find out on Saturday alright
thanks everybody and we'll see you then
you